Guide to the Carole Hyatt Papers 1947-2006 (bulk, 1980s-1990s) MS 3105
New-York Historical Society
Carole Hyatt papers
1947-2006 (bulk, 1980s-1990s)
New-York Historical Society
Hyatt, Carole
MS 3105
19 Linear feet in 19 boxes + 1.09 terabytes of digitized audiotapes
The Carole Hyatt papers include transcripts, notes, audiotapes, working files, and publicity material related to the author and career consultant Carole Hyatt's publications, workshops, and other initiatives. These especially relate to her trilogy of books exploring the relationship of individuals to a changing workplace: "When Smart People Fail" (1987), "Shifting Gears" (1990), and "Lifetime Employability" (1995), as well as to the ramifications of women's expanding role in the workplace. The collection holds about 670 audiotapes, principally of Hyatt's interviews with individuals and focus groups, which underlie much of her published work. About 450 of these have been digitized for access.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in four series:
Series I. Press, Publicity and Fan Letters, 1947-2006.
Series II. Research and Working Files, 1976-2005.
Series III. Audiotapes, 1975-2003, undated.
Series IV. Videotapes, circa 1980-2004, undated.
Biographical / Historical
Author, entrepreneur, and career consultant Carole Hyatt (née Schwartz) was born in 1935 in New York City. Her early life was directed toward the theatre, earning a Bachelor of Science degree in Theatre and Education from Syracuse University in 1956 and her Master of Arts degree in Children's Theater and Creative Dramatics from the University of Denver in 1959. In the early 1960s, with a focus on children's programming, Hyatt worked as a producer in theatre and, at CBS, in television. In 1966 she married Gordon Hyatt, whom she met at CBS. The Hyatts have one child, daughter Ariel.
In 1966, Hyatt co-founded, with social analyst June Esserman, the research firm Hyatt/Esserman Research Associates, later know as Child Research Service. Along with analyst Daniel Yankelovich, Hyatt and Esserman provided research services to corporations and other organizations on women, youth and family interaction issues, supporting the creation of products, services and marketing strategies by their clients. This work led to the publication of Hyatt's first books, "The Woman's Selling Game: How to Sell Yourself — and Anything Else" (1979) and "Women and Work: Honest Answers to Real Questions" (1980).
In 1982, Esserman died of a heart attack. With the loss of her partner, Hyatt sold the firm in 1983 to McCollum Spielman, though remaining on the Board of Directors until 1986. While constrained by a non-compete agreement until 1986, Hyatt began work on a new book, which would be published as "When Smart People Fail: Rebuilding Yourself for Success" (1987). She interviewed 176 people for the book from various fields, both the well-known and the not well known, to explore the career setbacks of individuals and how they recovered from them. Through the 1980s and into the mid-1990s, Hyatt continued conducting interviews with men and women concerning their relationship with the workplace and with one another as society shifted to a broader acceptance of women in the professional workforce. Interviews about surviving corporate downsizing and other corporate upheavals, changing careers and finding an identity outside of the corporate setting, and finding fulfillment in retirement, among other topics, led to Hyatt's next books: "Shifting Gears: How to Master Career Change and Find the Work That's Right for You" (1992) and "Lifetime Employability: How to Become Indispensable" (1995).
Hyatt took the lessons documented in her books and used them to create workshops that she ran for organizations. These workshops were aimed at both individuals, often women, empowering them to take charge of their careers and lives, and at teams of people, unlocking the creative energies of organizations, a process referred to as "ideation." Her appeal spread internationally, perhaps especially to Asia, notably Japan, where she had a close partnership with Sakayori Noriko in the translation and publication of her work. In addition to workshops, Hyatt was a frequent speaker at conferences, such as those of the National Association for Executive Women (NAFE).
Continuing to find new partnerships and vehicles for building out her essential messages, among other initiatives, Hyatt created the Leadership Forum in the late 1990s for improving career strategies and leadership qualities for women and, in 2013, Mission: Getting to Next as a career transition program for women.
(The above note was based on various on-line sources, including Wikipedia, as well as on documents in the collection.)
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers. The audio and videocassette tapes in the collection are restricted; see specifics at the series level below.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Carole Hyatt, 2016.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes transcripts, notes, audiotapes, working files, reference material, videotapes, and publicity material related to Carole Hyatt's publications and workshops. These especially relate to her trilogy of books exploring the relationship of individuals to a changing workplace: "When Smart People Fail" (1987), "Shifting Gears" (1990), and "Lifetime Employability" (1995). Also prominent in the working files are various concepts she researched for potential publication, such as the impact of women's increased earnings power on personal relationships and the attributes of successful couples. The range of Hyatt's activities are represented here, from books to workshops to corporate consulting to television programming possibilities. There is rich material on Hyatt's Japan initiatives of the 1980-1990s.
Hyatt's research files for her books of the 1980s and 1990s comprise a substantial portion of the collection. These include Hyatt's notes taken during her interviews and transcriptions of many of those interviews. The collection holds about 670 audiotapes, the bulk of which are of Hyatt interviews or recordings of her on radio interviews, making presentations, and the like. About 450 of these tapes have been digitized and can be listened to on-site at New-York Historical Society.
Businesswomen.; Career changes.; Career development.; Focus groups.; Interviewing; Man-woman relationships.; Organizational change -- United States.; Audiocassettes.; Letters (correspondence); Publicizing.; Transcripts.; Videotapes.
- Series I. Press, Publicity and Fan Letters, 1947-2006; 2.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes publicity material (brochures, advertisements, flyers, conference programs, tour schedules, etc.) for Carole Hyatt's books, speaking engagements, workshops, and other Hyatt appearances and initiatives; clippings, articles, tearsheets, and other documents from press outlets, including international sources, relating to Hyatt's books and appearances; and complimentary and appreciative "fan" letters sent to Hyatt.
  The bulk of the series dates from the late 1970s and into the early 2000s. However, there are a small number of documents representing Hyatt's early life and career (then still known as Carole Schwartz, prior to her marriage).
  Arrangement
  The bulk of the series was originally in 3-ring binders compiled by the Hyatts. The series opens with that material, though it was removed from the binders during processing.
  Following the unbound documents are similar publicity and press materials that were found by the processing archivist throughout the collection. A final folder includes documents from Hyatt/Schwartz's early life and career; the contents are noted at the folder level.
  - "The Selling Game" Press Book I (unbound) (2 folders), 1977-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - "The Selling Game" Press Book II (unbound) (2 folders), 1976-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - "Women and Work" & Other Publicity. Press Book (unbound) (2 folders), 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - "When Smart People Fail" Press Book I (unbound) (3 folders), 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - "When Smart People Fail" Press Book II (unbound), 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Shifting Gears" Press Book I (unbound), 1990-1997 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Shifting Gears" Press Book II (bound), 1986-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Asia / Japan / International Press Book (unbound), 1987-1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Lifetime Employability" Press Book (unbound) (2 folders), 1995-2001 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Press Book. General (unbound), 1990-2003 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fan Letters (unbound), 1976-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fan Letters. "When Smart People Fail" (unbound) (3 folders), 1982, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
  - Fan Letters (unbound) (2 folders), 1986-1992 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Fan Letters (unbound) (2 folders), 1993-1997 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Fan Letters; Gordon & Ariel Keepsake Letters (unbound) (2 folders), 1997-2002 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Miscellaneous Publicity: "When Smart People Fail", circa 1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Publicity: "Woman's Selling Game", 1983-1997 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Publicity: "Shifting Gears" (2 folders), 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - Miscellaneous Publicity: Leadership Forum Programs, 1997-2006 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Publicity: Speaking Engagements and Other, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings / Articles (2 folders), 1987-1990s (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings / Articles: International Press, 1980s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Various Early Documents and Stationery, circa 1947-1990s (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Holds three programs from theatre productions at the All Saints Parish House in Bayside, Long Island, in which Hyatt (then Carole Schwartz) performed in her youth (1947-48); a "how-to" booklet from Woman's Day for producing a childen's play "The Emperor's New Clothes," with a script by Schwartz (1962); four publicity photographs of Hyatt; letterhead stationery from Schwartz/Hyatt's various initiatives (including the Peppermint Players, ChildWays, etc.); two articles regarding Schwartz's child-oriented work (1960s); a circa 1980s brochure for McCollum/Spielman Associates' Child Research Services (originally co-founded by Hyatt); and other documents.
- Series II. Research and Working Files, 1976-2005; 6.5 Linear feet
  This series includes files with transcripts and notes from many of the interviews Carole Hyatt conducted in the 1980s and 1990s for her books, both those proposed and those realized, as well as for her many related initiatives. Some original audiotapes of the interviews are found here, filed with the transcripts (most audiotapes can be found in Series III).
  The series also holds Hyatt's general working files with remarks delivered at workshops and other venues; project proposals for books, television shows, partnerships, etc.; releases for interviews; reference material; and other documents.
  The files comprising this series were pulled together by the processing archivist from a variety of files in the collection, some well-ordered, others less so. Consequently, while the content of individual files remain as found in their original form and any perceived original connections among files was also retained, the overall arrangement and categorization of the material was established by the processing archivist.
  The series is organized in two subseries:
  Subseries II.A. Interview Transcripts and Notes, 1985-2002
  Subseries II.B. Working Files, 1976-2005
  - Subseries II.A. Interview Transcripts and Notes, 1985-2002; 3.6 Linear feet
    This subseries includes files of documents related to interviews conducted in the course of Hyatt's research for books published or for potential books and other initiatives. The files hold transcripts of the taped interviews or handwritten notes from the interview or both. Some files hold the cassette tape of the interview; those are noted in the container list. For the most, though, the related tapes were held apart from the document files and are found in Series III.
    Especially well-represented in this subseries are transcripts related to two of Hyatt's books "When Smart People Fail" (1987) and "Shifting Gears" (1990). Related material in the subseries that did not explicitly lead to a book but are concerned with the workplace of the late twentieth century, men and women's relation to the workplace, and the shifting notions of personal success are interviews on the themes of "corporate survivors," acquiring wisdom, and handling success. The evolving role of women in society is considered in interviews on the topic of winning (i.e., successful) couples and the impact on women of gaining financial power as they enter the workforce.
    A note on names: The form and spelling of names in the container list was taken from the documents. However, it is clear that variant forms and spellings of many of the names can be found in the overall collection, specifically between the transcripts and working documents (Series II) and the audiotape labels (Series III). The processing archivist noted some of these variant names, but surely not all, nor was any attempt made to reconcile them or determine a single "correct" name to use. Accordingly, users should keep in mind the potential for name variants and be cautious in relying exclusively on keyword searches.
    The subseries is arranged by research topic, with the two major topics first (Smart/Fail and Shifting Gears), followed by other well-defined themes advancing chronologically. Miscellaneous or less well-defined themes follow, also then advancing chronologically. For the most part, the processing archivist was able to discern the theme of the interview based on explicit markings, file structures, etc. Question marks were used in the label in cases of uncertainty.
    Archival folders were used to group thematic materials together and to sequence them in an accessible manner. However, the original folders were retained and the original contents were retained within those original folders. In part, this was done because the folders include notations. But it was also done for users to be able to perceive for themselves the visual clues potentially linking individual folders together thematically.
    Whenever tapes were found in a folder with, or very commonly wrapped inside, its related transcript/notes, the tape and documents were kept together. Documents/tapes now held in paper slings (i.e., not in an original folder) were generally found loose in the collection with no folder. To the extent the archivist could be reasonably sure of the topic, the material was placed in a subject category. Otherwise, these were mostly placed at the end of the subseries as unidentified topics.
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. A, circa 1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      5 files: Julie Anthony, Ann Arledge, Esther Ann Asch, Larry Atlas, Jean Avery.
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. B (3 folders), circa 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16-18)
      13 files: Barbara Babcock, Polly Bacca, Ben Barber, Barbara Barrie, Robert Baum, Polly Bergen, Jewelle Bickford, John Brademas, Peter Brav, David Brown, Richard Buckingham, Nolan Bushnell, Bob Butera/Jim Johnston
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. C, circa 1985 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      7 files: Marcia Cantarella, Ronald P. Carter, Vicki Carter, Richard Casey, Robert Cohen, Gerry Cooney, Walter Cronkite
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. D, circa 1985 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      5 files: Debra Darnall, J.B. Dixon, Mary J. Doherty, Debra Dorwell, Mickey Dwyer
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. E, circa 1985 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      5 files: Evelyn Echols, Ned Edwards, Lee Elman, Dan Erkkila, Aaron Esman
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. F, circa 1985 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      7 files: Mortimer Feinberg, Esther Ferguson, Manuel Fernandez, Maria Fitzgibbon, Tom Fitzgibbon, John Fletcher, Devon Fredericks
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. G, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      7 files: Susan Garcia, Charles Garfield, Don Gettinger, Peter Glankoff, Milton Glaser, Linda Gottlieb (in conversation with Carole Hyatt), Thomas Grey
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. H, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      8 files: Sonya Hamlin, Regina Herzlinger, Alice Heyman, John Hightower, Hank Horwitt, Michele Hughes, Carole Hyatt, Joan Hyler
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. J, K, L, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      8 files: Tom Jackson, Elaine Karsh, Ari Kiev, Beverly Kievman, Mackenzie Lee, Ilene Leff, Clare Booth Luce, Barbara Lundberg
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. M, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      3 files: Joseph Mackay, Roxanne Mankin, Jim Marini
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. N, O, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      4 files: Penny Naylor, Yvette Obadia, Kevin O'Connell, Dagmar O'Connor
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. P, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      4 files: Alexis Parks, Celia Paul (2 interviews), Sharon Poindexter
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. Q, R, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      9 files: Maureen Quilligan, Dennis Rappaport, Keith Reemstma, Jackie Reinach, Estelle Rosen, Jeffrey Rosen, Jane Ross, Ilana Rubenfeld, Wendy Rue
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. S (2 folders), circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
      16 files: Bert Salzman, Virginia Sandlin, Peter Schifter, Howard Schor, Cindy Schriebman, Kathrin Seitz, Ann Shanks, William L. Shirer, Norman Sieloff, Molly Siple, Jean Sisco, Ether D.G. Smith, Patricia Soliman, Ann Sperry, Anne Speilberg, Tina Spiro
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. T, U, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      7 files: Bill Tatum, Sharon Timmer, David Taylor, David Teitlebaum, Elizabeth and Nick Thomas, Mary Jean Tully, Stewart Unger
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. W (3 folders), circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 11-13)
      13 files: Nancy Walker, Michaela Walsh, Richard Weiss, Ira Wender, Av Westin, Ess White Jr., Susan Winer, Basil Winston, Dorothy Winston, David Wolper, Women's Focus Group in New York, Women's Focus Group in Detroit, Steve Wozniak
    - When Smart People Fail Interviewees. Y, Z, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      3 files: Frank Yablans, Daniel Yankelovich, Elaina Zucker
    - Shifting Gears Interviewees. A, circa 1988 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      2 files: Wally Amos, Barbara Ashley
    - Shifting Gears Interviewees. B, circa 1988 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      8 files: Mary Ann Baker, Ben Barber, Earlene Backes, Betsy Barlow (Rogers), Carole Bellamy, Norman Berman, Bruce Blythe, Ellen Bunin
    - Shifting Gears Interviewees. C-H, circa 1988 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      6 files: Marge Champion, Lily Dozier, Geraldine Ferraro, Fernando Flores, Linda Gottlieb, Dorothy Hafner
    - Shifting Gears Interviewees. J-K, circa 1988 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      7 files: Cynthia Johnson, Christopher Jones, Brice and Jeff Kaselsky, Mick Kelly, Virginia Kiser, Beverly Kievman, Tony Knerr
    - Shifting Gears Interviewees. L-S, circa 1988 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      6 files: Michael Lee, Rachel Matthews, Gifford Pinchot III, Barbra Rabke, Joe San Fellipo, Gloria Sokolin
    - Shifting Gears Interviewees. T-Y, circa 1988 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      6 files: Janet Throckmorton, Tom Wesselman, Ess White Jr., Basil Winston, Judy Woodfin, David Yarosh
    - Winning Couples Interviewees (4 folders), 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
      Surnames: Ambroises, Berenbeim, Fink, Frenkel, Glankoff, Green, Grode, Hyatt, Lapopala/Alexander, Lax, Long (2 tapes in file), Scudder, Valas, Vern (2 tapes in file),Widman
    - Winning Couples (?) Interviewees (2 folders), 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
      Surnames: Schwartz, Mankin (1 tape in file), Koff (1 tape in file), Malamud (2 tapes in file)
    - When Smart People Become Wise Interviewees. A-C, circa 1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      4 files: Diane Arden, Gail Blanke, Lois Brandt, Denise Cavanaugh
    - When Smart People Become Wise Interviewees. D-H, circa 1991 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      7 files: Deborah Daniels, Dean & Donna, Mary Flynn, Robert Gianetti and Lewis Kravitz, Carole Hyatt, Neil Hird, Jack and Ruth Hirscherwood
    - When Smart People Become Wise Interviewees. M-N, circa 1991 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      3 files: Thomas McCann, Louis Monari, Chris Nast
    - When Smart People Become Wise Interviewees. O-R, circa 1991 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      3 files: Carole Owens, Carolyn and Dominic Pascuzzi, Joanne Rogovia
    - When Smart People Become Wise Interviewees. S-W, circa 1991 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      6 files: Burt Salzman, Mark Schecter, John Tusconi, Nancy Weeren, Wisdom Group Sessions (one set of notes in the file refers to Corporate Survivors). One file holds miscellaneous notes on "Wisdom" and on "Retirement Interviews" which refers to several of the "wisdom" interviews.
    - Corporate Survivors Interviewees. Atlanta and Boston Focus Groups, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      The Atlanta group was men only, Boston was women only. Boston file includes 2 tapes.
    - Corporate Survivors Interviewees. B-D, circa 1991 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      4 files: Joel Brockner, Arnold Brown, Peggy Daniels, Tom Drucker
    - Corporate Survivors Interviewees. D-F, circa 1991 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      6 files: Detroit Focus Group, Jon Eliasen (1 tape in file), Larry Evans, Charles Freeman, Maureen Ferguson, Jane Friedman (1 tape in file)
    - Corporate Survivors Interviewees. G-H, circa 1991 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      5 files: Robert Gianetti and Lewis Kravitz, Debbie Goodstein (clippings only), George Haggerty, Nancy Hamlin and Joan Fox, Heather Harrington
    - Corporate Survivors Interviewees. J-K, circa 1991 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      3 files: Chris Jones, Eric Jones (2 tapes in file), Paul Kolton (2 tapes in file)
    - Corporate Survivors Interviewees. M-R, circa 1991 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      3 files: Maggie Melanson, Bonnie Maitlen, Ernan Roman
    - Corporate Survivors Interviewees. S-Y, circa 1991 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      4 files: Bill Semanie, Riifka Schoenfeld, Donald Yarnell, Tony Yadonga
    - Handling Success (1 folder of 3), 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      3 files: Hylan Booker (1 tape in file with Booker on one side and Gordon Hyatt on the other), Michael Desisto (1 tape in file), William O'Boyle
    - Handling Success Interviewees (2 folders of 3), 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
      4 files: Randy Rubin (1 tape in file), Barbara Udell (1 tape in file), Edie Wiener (1 tape in file), Women's Forum
    - Handling Success (?) Interviewees, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      1 file: John Harricharan (1 tape in file)
    - Pauses Interviewees (5 folders), 2001-2002 (Box 6, Folder 4-8)
      Opening file has "stories" of types of pauses. Named files: Denise Cavanaugh (1 tape in file), Paula Holt (1 tape in file), John and Anne Janas (1 tape in file), Joelle Norwood (2 tapes in file), P'An family (1 tape in file), Edie Wiener, Jen Deare (1 tape in file),Jeannie Fitzgerald (1 tape in file), Bill Kennedy (1 tape in file), Carolyn Wasserman (1 tape in file)
    - Working Mothers Interview, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      1 set of notes and 1 tape for interview with Edith Sims under working title "2nd Generation Working Mothers"
    - Interview about Milliken Company and Roger Milliken, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Transcript and 2 tapes with interviewee June Roache
    - Change/Attitude Interview, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      One transcript and one tape with interviewee Judith Gerberg
    - Heart and Marketing = Love Interviews, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Notes from two women's focus groups (Dallas and New York)
    - Time Management, [1996] (Box 6, Folder 13)
      Notes from one interview with Carol Coxwaite
    - Women and Earnings Power (?) Interviewees (4 folders), 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 14-17)